and we pick up now on קט"ו Kuf Tes Vav 115 and
we pick up at the bottom of קי"ד עמוד ב' Kuf Yud
Daled Amud Bais and we have just dealt with the משנה mishna
about a woman who reports that her husband died, that she is
believed in a case where there is not a known fight between
her and her husband going on, that their marriage is doing okay,
and that there's peace in the world. We will get to the
issue about the state of their marriage; the issue about the concern
about there being peace in the world is what the גמרא Gemara
says that if the world is in a state of war, she
might report that her husband is dead based on her interpretation of
the facts or her perception, כדדמי, k'didami, and not based on actual
concrete, clear knowledge. She'll see her husband shot and she'll assume he
died, and he won't necessarily have died. So the גמרא Gemara now
picks up with the following: it is 1, 2, 3, 6 lines
from the bottom, middle of the line, אמר רבא amar Rava on
קי"ד עמוד ב'. Kuf Yud Daled Amud Bais. Okay, so אמר רבא,
amar Rava, says רבא, Rava,
רעבון גריע ממלחמה; ra'avon gariya mimilchama; if it's a case of starvation,
that they are in the middle of a famine—not starvation, famine—that's if
she reported to say my husband died in the famine, so you
might think, well definitely yes because there of course it's not like
people are shooting guns and arrows and
so she'll make assumptions in the fog of war, there maybe she'll
know for definitely that he died. No, it's worse. Why? דאילו
מלחמה כי אמרה מת בעלי במלחמה הוא דלא מהימנא, המת
אמיתתו מהימנא.
de'ilu milchama ki amra meis ba'ali bemilchama hu
delo mehemana, hameis amitaso mehemana. In a case of war, he's only,
רבא Rava introduces an idea that is not at all clear in
the משנה, mishna, that in a case of war she's only not
believed if she says my husband died in the war. But if
she says it was the time of war and she says he
died on his bed, he had a natural death, she'd be believed.
Why not? Who cares that there's war waging in the
world? ואילו גבי רעבון אבל עד דאמרה מת וקברתיו ve'ilu gabei ra'avon
aval ad d'amra meis u'kvartiv until she says he died and I
buried him, because people will die on their bed in famine, they'll
die of starvation, and she won't necessarily be believed. Why not? Because
she'll think apparently that he has died and maybe people will faint
and look like they're dead at such a time when they haven't
actually died. So it's not so clear what the type of confusion
is that happens at a time of רעבון, ra'avon, a time of
famine, but רבא Rava says that there can still be confusion and
in a way it's worse because even something that looks like a
natural death she will not be believed in.
מפולת, Mapolet, now if we are dealing with a case of let's
say being trapped under a fallen building, הרי הוא כמלחמה,
hareihu kemilchama, then it is like, that's also like a מלחמה milchama
that she'll assume he died because the building collapsed and it won't
necessarily be the case.
דאמרה כדדמי, de'amra k'didami, that she'll say based on perception and on
what it looks like even if it's not definitely, even if it
hasn't definitely occurred. שילוח נחשים ועקרבים, Shiluach nechanishim ve'akravim, how about if
it's a time of snakes and scorpions? Okay, so the wild animals
in the place and maybe he even was bit by one, so
will she be believed? הרי הוא כן כמלחמה דאמרה כדדמי, hareihu ken
kemilchama d'amra k'didami, same same. So she's not believed, she'll say based
on perception, on how she interprets what has happened even if it
has not definitely occurred.
דבר, Dever, if it's a case of pestilence, אמרי לה הרי הוא
כמלחמה, amri lah hareihu kemilchama, some say also like a case of
מלחמה milchama that she'll think he's
died and he hasn't, ואמרי לה אינו כמלחמה, ve'amri lah eino kemilchama,
and some say it's not like מלחמה. milchama. אמרי לה הרי הוא
כמלחמה, amri lah hareihu kemilchama, same say it's like מלחמה milchama דאמרה
כדדמי, d'amra k'didami, she'll say based on things that look like it
even if it's not exactly it and her perception. ואמרי לה אינו
כמלחמה, ve'amri lah eino kemilchama, some say it's not like
מלחמה, milchama, דסמכא אדעתא, d'samchi ada'ata, that even if he has been
afflicted by pestilence or he's in a place where there is pestilence,
she's not going to make any assumptions. Why? Because there's a common
saying and what's the common saying? שב שנין הוה מותנא ואיש בלא
שניה לא אזיל, shev shanin havah moseina ve'ish belo shneih lo azil,
pestilence can go for seven years and a person won't die before
his time. So there's a general understanding that just because there is
a plague of pestilence, it doesn't necessarily mean that people will die,
that people can be very much in the middle of such a
plague and survive even in unlikely odds, and therefore because in that
case she will believe in unlikely odds, she won't make any assumptions.
But in these other things, there's no such thing, so she won't
believe in unlikely odds and the woman will draw some conclusions which
have not necessarily been the case.
Okay.
So
basically it's not specifically מלחמה, milchama, any type of a case where
we can assume that people are drawing incorrect, possibly incorrect conclusions. איבעיא
להו, Iba'ya lehu, they raised the question, last line of קי"ד עמוד
ב', Kuf Yud Daled Amud Bais, איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu, החזיקה היא
מלחמה בעולם מהו. hichzika hi milchama ba'olam mahu. Let's say we don't
know that there's war, she went to some foreign country. and she
comes back and she says war broke out there, my husband died
in the war. Is she believed? Because this is a classic case
of מיגו, migo, because she could she didn't have to say that
there was a war. So is she believed or not? מי אמרינן
מה לי לשקר, mi amrinan mah lo leshaker, should we say, look,
there's no need to lie, if she was just making this up
she could have said that there wasn't war. Top of קט"ו ע"א,
kuf tet vav amud aleph, אי
בעיא אמר שלום בעולם, i ba'ei amar shalom ba'olam, because she could
say that there was peace in the world. או דילמא, o dilma,
or do we say, כיון דאיחזקה, keivan de'ichzaka, since we now have
established that there is war, אמרה בדדמי, amra bidedamei, it doesn't matter
that we believe her sincerity and that she's telling the truth. We
still say that she might be making false conclusions even though she
believes them to be true. So this is the basic point that
מיגו migo only helps us ascertain that you're not intentionally lying. If
you had if you wanted to lie you'd say something else. Here
we don't think for a minute you're you're intentionally lying. So the
fact that you could have said something else doesn't matter, yes we
totally believe that you're being sincere. But the point is is that
even with all of your sincerity and desire to tell the truth,
maybe you're making some incorrect assumptions. So therefore that's the question about
will a מיגו migo help her situation at all. Now תוספות Tosafos
points out that in a way she always has a מיגו. migo.
Her standard מיגו migo is she could have said even at the
time of war that he died on his bed, he didn't die
in the war. And nevertheless
we don't believe her, because even though she has a מיגו. migo.
So you see that the מיגו migo does no good. All the
מיגו migo tells us is that she's not intentionally lying. So it
does raise the question why the גמרא Gemara thinks that this case
would be any better than a standard מיגו migo that she could
have said he died on his bed. So תוספות Tosafos deals with
that but again it proves the point that the מיגו migo is
not really
what's going to make a difference here. So let's take a look
what the גמרא Gemara says. רש"י Rashi I believe also raises the
question, one minute. Yeah,
so רש"י Rashi also raises the question. רש"י Rashi says a different
verb is another question, one minute. רש"י Rashi says like this,
oh no no רש"י Rashi has a different question which is that
if she's saying that he didn't
that there was she's obviously not saying...
well, forget it, let's move on. Okay, so anyway, so let's take
a look. תא שמע, ta shma, come and here. So כיון דאיחזקה,
keivan de'ichzaka, אמרה בדדמי, amra bidedamei, ולא אתו מה לי לשקר מרע
חזקתיה... velo atu mah lo leshaker mara chazkatei...
So do we say that even that on the one hand she
didn't have to lie, on the other hand even if she didn't
have to lie, now that we know and we don't think she's
lying, now that we know that there is war, she will make
false conclusions and the fact that she had no need to tell
the lie won't make a difference. Nevertheless she still she still and
we don't think she's intentionally lying we still think that she's just
reporting based on perception and not based on the concrete very concrete
knowledge of the facts. So what do we say? תא שמע, ta
shma, come and hear.
Okay. עישנו עלינו בית, ashinu aleinu bayis, עישנו עלינו מערה. ishnu aleinu
me'ara. Let's say she comes and tells us that the house filled
with smoke or the cave filled with smoke. הוא מת ואני ניצלתי,
hu meis va'ani nitzalti, and he died in the middle of the
smoke and I was saved. Okay, so that's similar to the war,
maybe she'll draw false conclusions. She escaped a burning house with smoke,
she'll assume he died, but maybe for all she knows she actually
escaped. So the ברייתא Baraisa says, אינן נאמנת, einan ne'emanus, she's not
believed. Now, that the גמרא Gemara says is a classic case of
we totally only know that the house was filled with smoke based
on her own testimony. Okay, so again the fact that we know
the circumstances based on her testimony doesn't make a difference. We still
assume that she's making incorrect drawing incorrect conclusions. So the גמרא Gemara
says, שאני התם, shani hasam, no, there it's different, even though she
didn't have to tell us that the house had filled with smoke.
דאמרי לה, de'amri lah, she'll say, we say to her, excuse me,
כהיכי דלדידי איתרחיש ניסא לדידיה נמי איתרחיש ניסא. keheichi delididi itrachish nisa
ledidei nami itrachish nisa. Look, you escaped a burning house filled with
smoke, so something a miracle happened to you, so maybe a miracle
happened to him. So we already have like in you yourself we
have a concrete evidence that something that you know that somebody could
have escaped from that situation and maybe that is what continues to
undermine her testimony or let us not base ourselves on base you
know assume draw conclusions from her testimony that he has actually died.
But maybe under normal circumstances if she's the one giving us all
the information maybe
we would assume the conclusions that she is drawing. Okay, so that's
the גמרא's Gemara question. So let's take a look. תא שמע, ta
shma, let's try it again. נפלו עלינו עובדי כוכבים, nafalu aleinu ovdei
kochavim, the non-Jews attacked us. נפלו עלינו ליסטים, nafalu aleinu listim, or
some bandits attacked us. הוא מת וניצלתי, hu meis venitzalti, he died
and I was saved. died and I was saved. Again, so something
that the two of us, it occurred to the two of us,
he died, I got out. So נאמנת, Ne'emenet, she's believed, and again
it's a similar situation where we wouldn't have known those circumstances were
it not for her, and nevertheless, I'm sorry, excuse me, the opposite.
So there we actually do believe her. So what makes that case
unique and different that we do believe her? Why don't we say
in that case also she'll say with incorrect perception? So the גמרא
Gemara says no. התם כרב אידי. Hatam kerav idi.
There the reason she's believed is like Rav Idi. דאמר רב אידי,
De'amar rav idi, אשה כלי זיינה עליה. Isha klei zaynah aleha. A
woman her, her weapons are on her. What does this mean? So
רש״י Rashi says that there because that there's that there's two things
going on there which makes it different than all the other cases.
The first thing is is that it happened uniquely to them. It's
not in the middle of a big war or a big pestilence,
it happened uniquely to them. And since it happened to the two
of them, she's it's more likely that the situation is less chaotic
and that she actually is able to report accurately about what happened.
Now, what about the fact that she escaped? Why don't we say
that if she escaped, then presumably he escaped as well like we
said before that even when there's a good reason to think that
those weren't the facts, if she managed to escape, maybe that should
make us assume that he's escaped as well. And for this the
גמרא Gemara answers this statement that a woman's weapons are on her,
which basically is a euphemistic way of saying, and another גמרא Gemara
says, that in a case where you're dealing with people that are
like people being attacked, a woman might will be saved when men
will be killed because people want to because the bandits, the robbers,
the non-Jews, whoever it is, want to save the woman in order
to rape her. So therefore it's more we can understand why the
woman would have escaped, maybe she wasn't raped, maybe she was being
saved in order to be raped and she managed to escape when
the man was not. Okay, so there's two things going on there.
Number one is what makes that less of a case of בדדמי
Bedidami is that it's only the two of them, it's not a
big chaotic situation. And what con- and what doesn't undermine the- and
by the fact that she was saved doesn't undermine the- the statement
that the man was killed is because we can understand why she
might have uniquely been saved, other than him. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues with the following. Okay, just one second. Right. So
רש״י Rashi says, התם כרב אידי בר אבין דאשה כלי זיינה עליה
הכא כיון דמלחמה קטנה היא דהואי
בהדדי לא
אמרה בדדמי.
Hatam kerav idi bar avin
de'isha klei zaynah aleha hacha
keivan demilchama ktana hi dehavi
behadadei lo
amra bedidami. It's a little war, right? So something that was only
the two of them, it was not as chaotic. So where we
are right now is that we say that, even if she didn't
have to- where it sounds like we're saying that even if she
didn't have to- where even if we didn't know that there was
war and she said it, the fact that she has no reason
to lie doesn't undermine the fact, doesn't change the fact that she
might have drawn wrong conclusions. And the only time that we do
believe her right now is the time where it was not a
big chaotic situation where it was just the two of them. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara continues with the following. ההוא גברא דבשילי
הילולא דאיטלי נורא בי גנני.
Hahu gavra debishilei hilula
deitli nura be ganenei. There
was a certain man that at the end of his wedding, at
the end of his, you know, נשואין, Nissu'in, the חופה, Chuppah, איטלי
נורא בי גנני, Itli nura be ganenei, a fire caught, you know,
caught, a fire broke out under his wedding חופה Chuppah or on
his wedding חופה. Chuppah. אמרה להו דביתהו. Amra lehu devithu.
So his wife said to the people standing around, חזו גבראי חזו
גבראי. Chazu gavrai chazu gavrai. Look my husband, he's on fire, come
help. אתו, Atu, people came. חזו גברא חרוכא. Chazu gavra charucha. By
the time they got there they found a charred person, a dead
body that was charred. דשדי. Deshadi. That was cast there. ופיסא דידיה.
Ufisa didey. And a hand, a severed hand. דשדי. Deshadi. That was
cast there. So סבר רב חייא בר אבין למימר היינו עשנו עלינו
בית עשנו עלינו מערה. Savar rav chiyya bar avin lemeimar hainu ishnu
aleinu bayit ishnu aleinu me'arah.
That's like the case that the house was filled with smoke, that
she's not believed because okay, there was a fire but who knows
what happened. Obviously there's a huge difference. What do you mean who
knows what happened? There's a dead body there.
So אמר רבא. Amar rava. Says Rava. מי דמי? Mi dami? Who
can compare it? התם לא קאמרה חזו גבראי חזו גבראי. Hatam lo
kaamra chazu gavrai chazu gavrai. First of all, in the case by
the house filled with smoke, she's not saying look at my husband,
look at my husband. So here she's calling people. So the fact
that she's calling people, you know, maybe also underscores the fact that
she has. she's seeing very concretely what's happening. It's not so clear
why the calling people itself makes a difference, but again we'll see
later in the גמרא Gemara that maybe the more that other people
can ascertain the facts, makes her more careful to be communicating very
concrete statements and facts and not any assumption. So number one is
she's calling people. But more significant is ועוד גבא חרוכא דשדי ופיסא
דידא דשדי. Ve’od gava charucha deshadi u-fisa deyada deshadi.
There's a charred body there and a charred hand. So there's very
concrete evidence that the husband died, if you look at all the
circumstances.
So רב חייא בר אבין Rav Chiyya bar Avin and so רב
חייא בר אבין Rav Chiyya bar Avin who did not want to
assume the husband died, he would say: גבא חרוכא דשדי אימא איניש
אחרינא אתא לאצולי ואכליה נורא. Gava charucha deshadi eima inish achrina ata
le’atzolei ve-achlei nura.
So the charred body, maybe it's not the husband. Maybe it's somebody
else who wanted to try to save the husband and the fire
consumed him. ופיסא דידא דשדי U-fisa deyada deshadi and the hand that
is charred that is not part of the same body, so דשדי
נורא איתצלי, deshadi nura italya, maybe the husband's caught on fire, ואיתעלי
במומא ve-italya be-muma
and this is the husband's hand and the husband became disfigured, his
hand burned, and this is his hand that fell off, ומחמת כיסופא
אזל וערק לעלמא u-machamat kisufa azal ve-arak le-alma
and because he's ashamed that he now is disfigured, he's run away,
and therefore this is the husband's hand and the husband has not
actually died. And look, you know, these situations about what conclusions you
can draw, you know, it's not just a question of what the
woman is saying. The, you know,
so often cases of עגונה, aguna, not because of a withholding of
a גט, get, because of questions about what happened to the husband,
are cases where
we know what happened but we don't know, nobody saw the dead
body. And what type of conclusions can you draw, right? So that's
like an example here, like we've got a dead body, we've got
the fire, we've got that it was under the wedding canopy. This
is no longer the case of אמרה בדדמי amra bididami where she
is saying, you know, she's saying it's my husband.
Maybe it is, but even if you put that aside, we are
looking at these facts, what conclusion can we reasonably draw from the
facts? Okay, so there's both a question about what do
we think that she is saying based on concrete knowledge, and then
there are also questions where even if we have all the facts,
what types of conclusions are we able to draw? But we're beginning
to see why it is that the rabbis might have been concerned
under some circumstances that someone's saying no I definitely saw him die
and given the sort of chaotic nature, what does that mean? If
you saw that there was a huge fire and he was in
a room, and then you saw that there was a body lying
there that was charred, would you go and report I definitely saw
him die? You know, that's not a big jump and from the
person's perception, especially during all of that the confusion, that totally might
be how the person is perceiving what types of dots a person
is connecting there. Of course, the big question that runs through all
of this is why aren't we investigating more and probing more and
asking her for concrete information and let that then become the basis
for drawing our conclusion based on how she answers our questions? And
that's really not clear at all. So what we have is that
the גמרא Gemara asked if the whole fact the claim of war
is coming from her, does that strengthen her statement? Hard to understand
why, since we're afraid that she is drawing incorrect conclusions, or you
know, making reasonable assumptions and interpreting facts, but not but it's not
really supported by absolute direct concrete evidence. And if that's true, but
she believes herself to be telling the truth, who cares if she's
reporting that there was war and we didn't know it without her?
Those are still legitimate concerns. And that seems to be where the
גמרא Gemara ended up, that the fact that she's reported war doesn't
help her, but then we have some situations where she is believed.
Either where it was not the chaos of war, it was just
the two of them were attacked, and that's actually a bit of
a surprise because you could think there too, just because it's the
two of them, she's running away, you know, who knows what assumptions?
So that's a surprise that she's believed there. And the other case
is the issue we just dealt with where there's actually some concrete
evidence. She's calling people, you see a charred body and so on.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. איבעיא
להו, Iba’ya lehu, they raised the following question: עד אחד במלחמה מהו?
Ed echad be-milchama mahu?
What about if it's not the woman, if it's one witness? Now
here again the funny thing is, why would we believe an impartial
person more than her if we're not afraid of lying, if it's
just a question about אמרה בדדמי, amra bididami, saying things based on
how things look and are perceived? So somehow there's an assumption that
when it's a third party because he is maybe less emotionally involved
in the situation, maybe because he is somehow, you know, less connected,
has less of a vested interest either way it comes out, but
also again is just able to be more objective, maybe because he's
concerned that by presenting himself not as a direct direct party but
as an as an as an independent witness then he's going to
be more careful about his testimony, right? He's not sort of saying
like, "Oh my god, my husband and I were attacked and this
happened," and then you're actually a subject of the story that you're
telling. Here you're presenting yourself—I mean, you also might have been a
subject, you were there in the battleground with the husband, but you're
presenting somehow you're presenting yourself more as an outside witness, and therefore
you'll be more careful. So somehow there's an assumption that if it's
a third party, he's going to be or she will be more
careful. And then the question therefore is, if a so if a
one witness says that the husband died in war, do we believe
him? Okay, so let's take a
look. איבעיא להו, Ibaia Lehu, so they raised the question: עד אחד
במלחמה מהו? Ed Echad Bemilchama Mahu? One witness, guy comes back from
the battlefield and says the husband died in in war. What's the
story? טעמא דעד אחד מהימנא, Ta'ama De'ed Echad Meheimna, and the normal
reason we believe one witness because remember this goes back to what
we learned in the earlier האשה Ha'ishah פרק Perek and what we'll
learn as we till the end of this מסכת Masechet about the
believability of one witness to say that the husband died, which was
the big חידוש Chiddush of the Rabbis, that normally you need two
witnesses. So is normal reason we believe one witness to say the
husband died דמילתא דעבידא לאיגלויי הוא, Demilta De'avida Le'igluyei Hu, that the
fact will eventually come clear, לא משקר, Lo Meshaker, and he won't
lie, הכא נמי לא משקר, Hacha Nami Lo Meshaker, here too he
won't lie because why would somebody lie about something that everybody's going
to find out the truth sooner or later? או דילמא, O Dilma,
or do we say טעמא דעד אחד משום דהיא גופא דייקא ומינסבא?
Ta'ama De'ed Echad Mishum Dehi Gufa Daika Uminisba? The reason that we'd
believe one witness is because it's it's backed up by the fact
that she's going to investigate herself and ascertain herself before she gets
married because of all the negative consequences that will occur if the
husband actually isn't dead. והכא לא דייקא ומינסבא. Vehacha Lo Daika Uminisba.
I'm going to take out the brackets. Here she won't. Why won't
she? Because what the גמרא Gemara says before, and the brackets are
very confusing what's in there. It says sometimes she hates him, which
has not been a concern of ours at all. So the without
the brackets or some replace the brackets with the word here on
the
side, לא דייקא ומינסבא דאמרה בדדמי, Lo Daika Uminisba De'amra Bedidami, because
again, she will say based on drawing certain conclusions and based on
perceptions and not based on facts. רש"י Rashi even without those words
in the גמרא Gemara says that what's the גמרא Gemara means. So
the degree that we need to rely on her, we've already established
that in her case, again, presumably it presumably it has nothing to
do with woman versus man, presumably even if the עד אחד Ed
Echad is a woman, but this has to do with the fact
that if she's so directly involved in the circumstances and emotionally involved
as well, she'll draw some incorrect conclusions. So if we need the
עד אחד Ed Echad to be backed up with her own
ascertaining of the facts, then that's not sufficient in this case. Or
and the way actually what רש"י Rashi also adds to that is,
maybe that's also why we won't believe him. Who cares if normally
he'll be very careful and say not say things that aren't true
because things will ultimately become to the surface and become known and
you'll be careful not to lie? Again, he doesn't think he's lying.
The issue is not whether he might be lying. The issue is
is he drawing wrong conclusions? So the argument to believe the to
not believe him is clear. We're concerned that people will make mistakes,
draw wrong conclusions. If it's true about the woman, it should be
true about him, and and anyway, if his testimony requires being backed
up by what she's able to determine, or what we assume she's
able to determine, we've already pointed out that that's a weak link.
The argument to believe him is less obvious, but presumably that's based
on the fact that the fact that he is a third party,
more not in directly involved in the issues, not as emotional as
emotionally involved, A, he may not in general
אמרה בדדמי Amra Bedidami say things based on perception not based on
fact, and B, because he's presenting himself as a witness, it really
has to do with, you know, his integrity and therefore more than
somebody who was like directly a party to the fact then he's
and think the facts will eventually come to the surface, עבידא לאיגלויי,
Avida Le'igluyei, he's going to be very careful not just not to
lie, but very careful to say things that are only very precise
and and very concrete knowledge. So that's the question of do we
believe the עד אחד? Ed Echad? So let's take a look. אמר
רמי בר חמא, Amar Rami Bar Chama, said
רמי בר חמא, Rami Bar Chama, תא שמע, Ta Shema, come and
hear. אמר רבי עקיבא, Amar Rabbi Akiva, said רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
כשירדתי לנהרדעא לעבר שנה, Kesheyaradeti Lenehardea Le'aber Shanah, when I went to
נהרדעא Nehardea to make the leap year, which raises interesting questions: when
are you allowed to make a leap year, an extra month, right
outside of ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? It's supposed to be done only
in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So that has to do with the
fact that if there's nobody in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael who's of
the same level, you can do it outside ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Very important ideas that applied in the big debate in the big
power struggle after the in the time of the גאונים Geonim between
whether the center was בבל Bavel or ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and
who had the authority. There was a whole debate about whether you
about making a leap year and in the end בבל Bavel won
out because they said nobody is, you know, there's nobody equivalent to
the גאוני בבל Geonei Bavel in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. We are
the seat of authority. So anyway, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said when
I went to נהרדעא Nehardea in order to make the leap year,
מצאתי. Matzati. נחמיה איש בית דלי, Nechemia Ish Beit Dali, I found
this man נחמיה Nechemia from the house of בית דלי, Beit Dali,
ואמר לי, ve'amar li, and he said to me, שמעתי שאין משיאין
את האשה בארץ ישראל על פי עד אחד, shamati she'ein mashi'in et
ha'isha be'Eretz Yisrael al pi ed echad, I heard that in the
land of Israel they will not marry a woman based on one
testimony, אלא רבי יהודה בן בבא, ella Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava, the
only one who will do it is רבי יהודה בן בבא. Rabbi
Yehuda ben Bava. So is that meaning just סתם stam one witness
saying a husband died, which is something that we've been taking for
granted now for a long time, or is that specifically the case
of saying he died in war? Anyway, this is what he said,
that there's only one person who will do that. ועניתי לו, ve'aniti
lo, and I said to him, כן הדברים, ken hadevarim, that is
correct. אמר לי, amar li, he said to me, אמור להם, emor
lahem, go back and tell them
משמי, mishmi, in
my name, אתם יודעים המדינה הזו משובשת בגייסות. atem yode'im hamedina hazzo
meshubeshet begayasot. You know that this country, נהרדעא Nehardea presumably, is, you
know, messed up, is somehow, you know, unstable
due to army troops that go through
it. כך מקובלני מרבן גמליאל הזקן, kach mekubbanni meRabban Gamliel haZaken, this
is the tradition I have from רבן גמליאל הזקן, Rabban Gamliel the
Elder, שמשיאין את האשה על פי עד אחד, shemashi'in et ha'isha al
pi ed echad, that you can allow a woman to remarry on
the basis of
one testimony. Now what is he saying? What does it have to
do with the troops? And are we talking about a case of
war, not a case of war? He did mention troops. What is
the issue about marrying off a woman? What are the circumstances of
marrying off a woman based on עד אחד? ed echad? So let's
see what the
גמרא Gemara says. מאי מדינה משובשת בגייסות? mai medina meshubeshet begayasot? What
does he mean to say that this country is, you know, chaotic
or unstable due to troops, army troops? לאו, lav, does he not
mean to say, אף על גב דמדינה זו משובשת, af al gav
demedina zo meshubeshet, even though this country is in a state of
war and there are troops going, you know, back and forth, nevertheless
כך מקובלני שמשיאין על פי עד אחד, kach mekubbanni shemashi'in al pi
ed echad, that the point is that you believe one witness in
a time of war and that's why he mentioned troops and that's
what's at stake and he says that that is actually his tradition?
So you see that you do marry off a woman based on
one witness at a time of war. אלמא עד אחד מהימן, alma
ed echad meheman, you see one witness is believed. אמר רבא, amar
Rava, says רבא, Rava, no. אי הכי מאי שנא מדינה זו? ei
hachi mai shena medina zo? Why does he say this country, נהרדעא,
Nehardea, we have this problem of troops? Why not just say, he
was talking about what they did in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, what
their
halakhic position was in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, so why not just
say that when a country is in a state of war, nevertheless
you believe על פי עד אחד? al pi ed echad? אלא אמר
רבא, ella amar Rava, rather said רבא, Rava, כל מקום שיש גייסות
מיבעי ליה, kol makom sheyesh gayasot mibei lei, it should have said
whenever there are troops, you still believe based on עד אחד. ed
echad. אלא אמר רבא, ella amar Rava, rather said רבא, Rava, הכי
קאמר, hachi ka'amar, this is what he
means. אתם יודעים שהמדינה הזו משובשת בגייסות atem yode'im shehamedina hazzo meshubeshet
begayasot ואי אפשר לי למשבק אינשי ביתי ומייתי קמי רבנן. ve'i efshar
li lemishbak inshi beiti umaytei kamei rabbanan. You know that it's very
impossible, it's impossible to travel nowadays. There are all these troops and
we're in a state of war and I can't get to ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but again remember the focus of the discussion was
what is the פסק psak in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So he's
saying, look, I can't go and tell them myself in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael my tradition from רבן גמליאל הזקן Rabban Gamliel the Elder
because we're in a state of war. You go and you go
back and when you get back there, you tell them what the
הלכה halakha is. כך מקובלני מרבן גמליאל שמשיאין את האשה על פי
עד אחד. kach mekubbanni meRabban Gamliel shemashi'in et ha'isha al pi ed
echad. But here's my tradition, that you marry a woman based on
עד אחד, ed echad, but it has nothing to do with in
a time of war. That's just why he can't tell them himself.
So we don't know from that story whether what was at stake
was in general believing in עד אחד, ed echad, which we take
very much as a for granted, and then it would be a
little bit shocking slash surprising that in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael already
by the time of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva towards the end of
the period of the תנאים, Tannaim, there's only one opinion that you
could marry off a woman based on a single witness, you know,
that the husband had died. We've been assuming that that is a
completely universal assumption. So that's one version of it. The other version
is the specifically what was at stake was the issue of believing
in עד ed at a time of war or about death during
circumstances of war. So we don't know exactly how to interpret that.
תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear.
So
this is still our question believing in עד אחד ed echad in
a situation of
war. מעשה בשני תלמידי חכמים שהיו באים עם אבא יוסי בן
סימאי בספינה. ma'aseh bishnei talmidei chachamim shehayu ba'im im
Abba Yossi ben Simai bisefina. There were two Torah sages
that
were coming with אבא יוסי בן סימאי Abba Yossi ben Simai in
a boat. וטבעו, vetavu, and
they both sank. והשיא רבי נשותיהן על פי נשים. vehesi Rabbi nishoteihen
al pi nashim. And רבי Rabbi let their wives remarry based on
the testimony of women. Some women saw the boat sink or survived
on the life raft and רבי Rabbi said that based on the
fact that they said the husbands were there and they sank, he
allowed the wives, the wives weren't the ones reporting, other women were
reporting, he allowed the wives to remarry. So now the גמרא Gemara
says מים כמלחמה דמי. mayim kemilhama dami. Water is like war in
the sense that people will generally say based on perception, not based
on concrete, you know, absolute concrete knowledge. Things are very chaotic and
confusing and people will draw assumptions. And these are not the woman
herself, but a third party, and... And the גמרא Gemara says and
it's not a case of two witnesses, a formal two witnesses. How
do you know
that? Because בנשים אפילו מאה כאחד דמי, bi'nashim afilu me'ah k'echad dami,
so you know statements in the גמרא Gemara that are like legally
legal statements but also a little bit jarring. A hundred women is
like one, but not like one man here it tells like one
witness, which means that no matter how many women witnesses you have
they never create the two formal male witnesses that are necessary in
terms of that sense of formal testimony, so they always have the
status of informal testimony which is the same as one male witness.
So here you have a case of informal
testimony, the report of a person, one person or you know that
is that does not count as formal testimony, and you are believing
it. So this is exactly our case of עד אחד במלחמה, ed
echad b'milchama, one witness, meaning not two men formal witnesses but one
witness or women or whatever the case is that are not the
parties themselves, and they might be drawing wrong conclusions. But nevertheless because
they are not the parties themselves, you actually don't are not concerned
about a misreporting and you actually can take that testimony. So that
seems to be good evidence. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says: וקתני השיא
v'katani
heishi that רבי Rebbi married off their
husbands—not the women, sorry, not those that are testifying—married, excuse me, married
off the women of the people that were reported to be dead.
So ותסברא v'tisbra says the גמרא, Gemara, is that really true? מים
שאין להם סוף נינהו, mayim she'ein lahem sof ninhu, this is water
that has no end. ומים שאין להם סוף אשה אסורה, u'mayim she'ein
lahem sof isha asura, we would never, even if there were two
witnesses that said we saw a man drown in water without an
end, you would not let the woman remarry. What does that mean,
water without an end? It means that you cannot see
all of the shores that surround the water. Why does that matter?
If anything you would see it's more likely that the guy had
died; there's no shore for him to swim to. But no, the
concern is is that if you can't see the end of the
water, then maybe he survived and he's somewhere in the water outside
of your sight, right? And therefore if it's such a vast body
of water that you can't see the edges of, any report that
he drowned is never an absolute report; he might have gone under
the water and you and ultimately he would have survived. So the
גמרא Gemara is saying I don't get this case anyway. How did
you allow for remarry? Presumably, I don't know how the גמרא Gemara
knew that this was a case of אין להם סוף, ein lahem
sof, but that was the assumption of the גמרא. Gemara. So therefore
how could even with, you know, a two formal witnesses, there's this
story doesn't make sense. So the גמרא Gemara says: אלא היכי דמי,
ela heichi dami, what must be the case? דאמרי אשכחינהו קמן d'amri
ashkachinhu kaman that they say no actually we saw the body, the
body was brought in front of
us, וחזינהו לאלתר, v'chazinahu l'altar, and we saw him immediately. The immediate
point is so that the water has not completely disfigured the body.
ואמרי סימנים v'amri simanim and they say marks and they say marks
and they say סימנים simanim and they say that we actually saw
some bodily marks, you know, we saw a mole, we saw a,
you know, he had a, he had a, you know, he had
some type of a weird birthmark or he had a dislocated shoulder.
Whatever they saw, they saw things that were very—that were unique signs
on the body. And therefore that might be needed. תוספות Tosafot discusses
why do they need סימנים? simanim? Why can't they say we recognize
the face? So it could be once they were in the water
for a little bit, the face is a little disfigured—it's not completely
disfigured—but you need it to be reinforced by the presence of certain
very like identifying marks on the body. So therefore in that case
דלאו עלייהו סמכינן אלא אסימנים, d'lav aleiyhu samchinan ela a'simanim, we're not
relying on them; we're relying on the very specific bodily marks that
they identified. So basically there's no concern there of אמרי בדדמי amri
b'didami that people are saying based on perception. They saw actually the
body, sort of like the case before about the charred body, but
this is even better than the charred body because the charred body
there was an assumption of whose body it was. Here there were
actually סימנים simanim and therefore
and therefore we have very concrete evidence. So the גמרא Gemara has
not really concluded whether or not you believe in עד אחד, ed
echad, and that's obviously a huge issue, right? Is it that you
only believe in עד אחד ed echad in normal reports—"Oh yeah, the
guy passed away normally"—or do you believe in עד אחד ed echad
in cases where things are somewhat chaotic and a war, fallen buildings?
Just think about 9/11, you know, and are we willing to believe
even in that situation or we concerned that people draw wrong conclusions?
Of course the part that's missing from all of this is why
you so concerned that people are drawing wrong conclusions? Just ask very
concrete questions and get to the bottom of it and figure out
if you believe that they're telling the truth, then just clarify more
what it actually means what they are saying. So that obviously is
a key part that is missing from this גמרא. Gemara.
Let's
now take a look at another story, two lines from the top
here on
קטו עמוד ב: kuf tes vav amud beis: ההוא גברא דאפקיד שומשמי.
hahu gavra d'afkid shumshmi. Now we're going to go from a very...
weighty case about people dying and drowning and burning to a דיני
ממונות dinei mamonot case about sesame seeds, okay, and we will see
an interesting analogy that the
גמרא Gemara brings. ההוא גברא דאפקיד שומשמי גבי חבריה. Hahu gavra de-ifkid
shumshumei gabei chavreih. A certain person gave as a for safe keeping
a certain amount of sunflower seeds to his friend. אמר ליה הב
לי שומשמי Amar lei hav li shumshumei and after a while he
said give me back my sunflower seeds. אמר ליה שקילתינהו. Amar lei
shekaltinehu. You already took them back a while
ago. והא כיילא וכיילא הויין? Ve-ha kaila ve-kaila havyan? What do you
mean? It was, I gave you exactly three pounds of them ובחביתא
רמיין u-ve-chavita ramyun and they were in that barrel and they walked
over and there are three pounds of sesame seeds in that
barrel. אמר ליה דידך שקילתינהו והני אחריני נינהו. Amar lei didach shekaltinehu
ve-hanei achrinei ninhu. No, you took yours
back, these are other sunflower seeds, these are my sunflower
seeds. סבר רב חסדא למימר. Savar Rav Chisda le-meimar. So רב חסדא
Rav Chisda wanted to
say: היינו הני שני תלמידי חכמים. Haynu hanei shenei talmidei chachamim. This
is like the case of the two sages that drowned and the
question was were they the same people or not? And there he
assumed that, bracketing our discussion a minute ago about the סימנים, simanim,
he assumed that, you know, they were on the boat, you found
two bodies, you made certain assumptions that they are, you know, they
looked the same, presumably they were the same people. So here too,
you know, it looks like the same, same amount, and you're going
to assume it's the same sunflower seeds. Of course the application from
remarrying wives to issues of sunflower seeds, you know, A: would we
apply different standards of proof, number one, and number two also, like
how much, you know, what's the concrete facts, how much circumstantial and
context and evidence is there in one case versus how much in
the other. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with it.
The גמרא Gemara says: הני שני תלמידי חכמים. Hanei shenei talmidei chachamim.
That's like the case of the two
Torah sages. ולא אמינא הנך אזלו לעלמא והני אחריני נינהו. Ve-la amina
hanach azlu le-alma ve-hanei achrinei ninhu. We don't say, yeah, those two
guys that were on the boat they are drowned at the bottom
of the sea and these two bodies are other bodies. No, we
assume two guys drowned and we drew out two bodies, it's the
same two
bodies. אמר ליה רבא. Amar lei Rava. So רבא Rava said: מי
דמי? Mi dami? How can you compare
it? התם קאמר סימנים. Hatam ka-amar simanim. In that case they gave
identifying marks. Of course, you know, that wasn't explicit in the case
before, that's what the גמרא Gemara says, so רב חסדא Rav Chisda
might not have been assuming that. רב חסדא Rav Chisda might have
assumed: two bodies, two bodies, you match it up. But רבא Rava
said no, we said that the case was only a case where
there were identifying
marks. הכא שומשמי מאי סימני אית להו? Hacha shumshumei mai simanei it
lehu? Here there's no identifying marks. ותיקמא? Ve-tikma? The גמרא Gemara says:
what do you mean? והא כיילא וכיילא הויין? Ve-ha kaila ve-kaila havyan?
But and the fact that he said oh it was exactly three
pounds and they found it was three pounds, isn't that an identifying
mark? אמר חושבנא איתרמי. Amar chushbana itremi. No, maybe it just so
happened that it was the same amount, that three pounds and three
pounds is not such an identifying mark. It's like saying that the
body was, he was 5'4" and this guy is 5'4". You know
what? A lot of guys that are 5'4", especially Jewish guys. There
are a lot of times that you might have three pounds of
sunflower seeds and that's not enough of an identifying mark. Okay, so
again what's more interesting here is rather than the דיני ממונות dinei
mamonot case itself, you know, is the fact about how much do
you use certain circumstances. On the one hand the whole problem of
the woman is אמר בדדמי. amar bi-dedami. On the other hand, as
we saw about the charred body and as we're sort of trying
to figure out here how much identifying marks there were on the
guys, what if we actually do know the facts, but it's not
a hundred percent, we do have to connect some dots and draw
some conclusions. Are we ever able to אמר בדדמי, amar bi-dedami, make
some conclusions based on the facts and based on context? And then
the question is how many jumps can we make? Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר ליה מר קשישא בר רב
חסדא לרב אשי. Amar lei Mar Kashisha bar Rav Chisda le-Rav Ashi.
So מר קשישא בר רב חסדא Mar Kashisha bar Rav Chisda said
to רב אשי: Rav Ashi: ומי חיישינן שמא פינן? U-mi chayshinan shema
pinan? Are we really a concern back to the in the sunflower
case that maybe he, you know, took out the sunflowers from the
barrel seeds and put in other sunflower
seeds? והתנן, Ve-hatnan, we learned in the משנה: Mishnah: מצא כלי וכתוב
עליו. Matza kli ve-katuv alav. If you found a vessel and written
on it is קוף, Kuf, then you can assume that that means
קרבן. Korban. That means that the stuff in it, whether it's money,
whether it's grain or whatever, was sanctified for הקדש, Hekdesh, קרבן Korban
being symbolic of הקדש, Hekdesh, maybe specifically to be used as a
קרבן Korban or to gift to הקדש. Hekdesh. מם, Mem, if there's
a מם Mem on the vessel, מעשר, Maaser, it means that the
grain in it is grain that is stored for מעשר. Maaser. דלת,
Dalet, דמוע. Dimua. דלת Dalet is a mixture that accidentally when חולין
Chullin and תרומה Terumah get mixed up together. טית, Tet, טבל. Tevel.
טית Tet is a sign of a vessel containing grain that has
not had תרומות ומעשרות Terumot u-Maasrot removed from it. תיו, Tav, תחת
תרומה. tachat Terumah. So sorry, תיו, Tav, תרומה, Terumah, and תיו Tav
is for תרומה. Terumah. Okay, so that's what you can assume is
in this
vessels. שבשעת סכנה היו כותבין תיו תחת תרומה. She-be-shaat sakana hayu kotvin
Tav tachat Terumah. At the time of danger they would write תיו
Tav instead of תרומה Terumah because they would not be allowed to
take תרומות ומעשרות Terumot u-Maasrot or, you know, religious practices were forbidden,
so therefore they would just do it this way. Of course, even
I don't know why you have to introduce שעת הסכנה. Sha'as Hasakanah.
Why do people have to write a whole word if you know
one letter can suffice? Anyway, the point being that you assume that
the stuff that was stored in that vessel was the stuff that
was originally put there and not that the vessel was emptied and
other stuff was put in its place. Now, of course, the point
is, yeah, because if you have your vessels labeled, like what's the
likelihood you're going to put salt in your sugar bowl, you know?
I mean, the reason for labeling them is so that you're consistent
in terms of what you keep in them. So, but maybe it's
a while since this vessel, maybe this vessel was found buried somewhere
and who knows? Or you know, maybe you assume somebody reused it.
Anyway, from this the גמרא Gemara draws a conclusion that we're not
assume that things are emptied and reused.
So
here, how come by the sunflower seeds are we assumed that the
guy took the sunflower seeds out and somebody else and he put
his sunflower seeds in in their place? So the גמרא Gemara says
אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי, Amar lei Ravina le-Rav Ashi, ולא חיישינן
שמא פינה? Velo chaishinan shema pina? Are we not concerned that somebody
might empty out a vessel and then reuse it for something else?
אימא סיפא, Eima seifa, look at the
end. רבי יוסי אומר אפילו מצא חבית וכתוב עליה תרומה, Rabbi Yosei
omer afilu matza chavis ve-kasuv aleha terumah, even if you found a
whole barrel and explicitly was written on the barrel the word תרומה,
Terumah, הרי אלו חולין, Harei elu chullin, you can say that what's
in the barrel now is
חולין. Chullin. שאני אומר אשתקד הוי מלאה תרומה, Shani omer eshtakad havei
meleiah terumah, because I could say last year you used it for
תרומה, Terumah, ופינה, U-pina, you emptied it out and now you're using
it for something else. So you see it is quite possible that
we assume that even something that was stored in a vessel is
no longer the original
thing. אלא דכולי עלמא חיישינן שמא פינה, Ella de-chulei alma chaishinan shema
pina, it must be that in general we are concerned that things
might be emptied and then reused for something else. והכא בהא קמיפלגי,
Ve-hacha be-ha kamifligi, here's the debate in terms of the
תרומה Terumah situation. מר סבר אם איתא דפניה מיכפר הוה כפר, Mar
savar im issa de-panya michpar hava kafar, one says if you were
going to use the vessel for something else, you would have erased
the letter that said ת Tav for תרומה, Terumah, right? You would
not, you have something there that marks what it's about. So you're
not going to, you might sure reuse a vessel, but you're not
going to leave it with the wrong marker on it, which is
a very reasonable concern. ואידך חמא, Ve-idach chama, and the other one
says, אישתלויי אישתלי, Ishtaluyei ishtali, you forgot that you had it labeled,
and therefore you might use it for something else. אי נמי לפתחיה
שבקיה, Ei nami l-fitchaya shavkeih, or maybe you intentionally kept stuff there
with the marking of תרומה Terumah as a way of protecting it.
You figured if it's not marked תרומה, Terumah, people are going to
eat it, but if it's marked תרומה, Terumah, people won't touch it,
and that's a way to protect it. So that's uniquely a concern
by things that have an explicit label on them, that the label
will indicate that you're consistent with the use. But things without the
label, like the sunflower seeds and whatever, it's very reasonable that, I
mean, maybe if the barrel was labeled שמעון's Shimon sunflower seeds, that
would be a similar circumstance. But since it was in a generic
barrel, we can assume, it's reasonable to assume that maybe he gave
his, he gave the guy his stuff back and he then put,
you know, he gave שמעון Shimon his sunflower seeds back and then
he put his sunflower seeds in their place. Okay, so that was
an interesting application. And again, interesting about whether we're going to have
similar or different standards for דיני ממונות Dinei Mamonos as opposed to
remarrying a woman based on testimony that the husband is dead. But
again, questions about what types of circumstances and context let us connect
the dots. We're so concerned that he's connecting the dots and misreporting
based on assumptions, sometimes we have to be the ones connecting the
dots anyway. Okay, so where are we right now? We are number
one with the assumption that a woman is not believed because we're
assuming she's drawing wrong conclusions, and it's just not limited to war.
It applies to other things as well. We are
also, though, said that there are some cases where she is believed.
Number one, if she says that he died under normal circumstances. B,
maybe if she's the one reporting on the war, although we are
concerned that he might be drawing wrong conclusions, somehow she's reporting on
the war, that'll make her more careful and more precise. Not exactly
clear why. So there seemed the inclination of the גמרא Gemara was
not to believe her in those cases. On the other hand, if
there's a third party, an עד אחד, Ed Echad, although he also
might be drawing some conclusions, somehow the fact that he's a third
party might make him more careful and more precise and not say
based on perceptions. And then there's the issue about whether we ourselves,
under what circumstances will we draw the right conclusions? Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara continues,
two
dots about 15 lines from the bottom. יצחק ריש גלותא בר אחתיה
דרבי ביבי. Yitzchak Reish Galusa bar achateih de-Rabbi Bibi. So יצחק, Yitzchak,
the ריש גלותא, Reish Galusa,
he was actually the political head of the Jews in בבל, Bavel,
and he was the son of the sister of רבי ביבי, Rabbi
Bibi, okay. הוה קאזיל מקורטבא לאספמיא. Hava ka'azil mi-Kortava le-Aspamya.
He was going from קורטבא, Kortava, I don't know what that is,
maybe it's Cordoba, but to אספמיא Aspamya to
Spain. ושכיב, Ve-shachiv, right? So here he is. He's not just, not
just in בבל, Bavel, like you know, he's responsible for the whole
diaspora. So he was on a trip, you know, maybe a type
of a, of a political tour. And anyway, he passed away. but
to אספמיא *Aspamya* to Spain. ושכיב *ve-shakhiv*, right? So here he is.
He's not just in בבל *Bavel*, like, you know, he's responsible for
the whole diaspora. So he was on a trip, you know, maybe
a type of a political tour, and, anyway, he was taking this
trip and he died. שלחו מהתם *shalkhu me-hasam*, so they sent the
following message: יצחק ריש גלותא Yitzchak Reish Galuta *Yitzchak Reish Galuta*, יצחק
*Yitzchak* the head of the exile, בר אחתיה דרב ביבי *bar achatei
de-Rav Bibi*, the son of the sister of רב ביבי *Rav Bibi*,
הוה קאזיל מכתובא לאספמיא *hava ka-azil mi-Katova le-Aspamya*, was traveling from Cordoba
to אספמיא *Aspamya* to Spain, ושכיב *ve-shakhiv* and he died. So that's
very precise information. It's not a case of מלחמה *milchama*. You know,
it's certainly מילתא דעבידא לאיגלויי *milta de-avida le-igloyei*. What type of a
concern can there be? So let's take a look. מי חיישינן לתרי
יצחק או לא *mi chayishinan le-trei Yitzchak o lo*? Are we concerned
that there might be two people with the same name, two יצחקs
*Yitzchaks*? Now this, of course, seems so absurd. How many יצחקs *Yitzchaks*
are there that are the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta *Reish Galuta*, the
son of the sister of רב ביבי *Rav Bibi*? So it seems
like a very bizarre concern because there are all of these very
clearly identifying information. Anyway, let's see where the גמרא *Gemara* goes with
this. But let's sort of not worry ourselves right now about why
it's relevant exactly to this, but let's just ask in general the
question. You know, we get a message: שמעון *Shimon* the son of
ראובן *Reuven* from this town died. Do we have to be concerned
that there might be somebody else with that name? This is a
place where you didn't have Social Security numbers, you didn't have family
names, you know. How much identifying information do you need to know
who we're talking about? Again, in this case, it seems like there
was plenty of identifying information. But let's see what the גמרא *Gemara*
says. מי חיישינן לתרי יצחק או לא *mi chayishinan le-trei Yitzchak o
lo*? אביי Abaye אמר חיישינן *Abaye amar chayishinan*, we are all concerned
that somebody else might have the same name. רבא Rava אמר לא
חיישינן *Rava amar lo chayishinan*, we're not concerned. אמר אביי Abaye *amar
Abaye*, says אביי *Abaye*, מנא אמינא לה minah amina lah, *mena amina
lah*, where do I know this that we don't assume that just
because we can, we know a guy by that name, that it's
necessarily the same guy? דההוא גיטא דאשתכח בנהרדעא *de-hahu gita de-ishtakhach bi-Nehardea*,
there was a גט *get* found in נהרדעא *Nehardea*, וכתיב *ve-khtiv*, and
it was written in the גט *get*, בצד פלוניא מתא *be-tzad pelonya
mata*, by the, you know, in the environs of the city of
פלוניא *Pelonya*, אנא אנדרולינאי *ana Androlinai*, I, אנדרולינאי *Androlinai*, מנהרדעא
*mi-Nehardea*, פטרית ותרכית ית פלונית אינתתי *patrit ve-tarkhit yat pelonit inteti*, I
have divorced and sent away so-and-so my wife, ושילחה *ve-shilchah*, and I
have sent her
away. ושדרוה אבוה דשמואל *ve-shadruah avuh de-Shmuel*, ושדרוה אבוה דשמואל *ve-shadruah avuh
de-Shmuel* לקמיה דרב יהודה נשיאה *lekamei de-Rav Yehuda Nesi'ah*, the father of
שמואל *Shmuel* sent this גט *get* to the presence of רב יהודה
נשיאה *Rav Yehuda Nesi'ah*, the grandson of רבי יהודה הנשיא *Rabbi Yehuda
HaNasi*, and wanted to know: can I assume that this guy is
the person we know from נהרדעא *Nehardea* of the same name? ושלח
ליה
*ve-shalach leh*, and he sent back to him, זיל בדוק בנהרדעא כולה
*zil bedok bi-Nehardea kullah*, you have to, you know, check the entire
נהרדעא *Nehardea* to find out if there is somebody else that has
the same name.
You know, we know, now רש"י *Rashi* even points out that it
said, "I, אנדרולינאי *Androlinai*, the husband of שרה *Sarah* from נהרדעא *Nehardea*
divorced my wife." And we know a guy in נהרדעא *Nehardea* called
אנדרולינאי *Androlinai* whose wife's name is שרה *Sarah*. Like, we know somebody
who matches the entire description. Can we just assume it's the guy
we know, or do we have to be concerned maybe there's another
guy in נהרדעא *Nehardea* with the same name whose wife has the
same name? So that was the question, and the answer of רב
יהודה נשיאה *Rav Yehuda Nesi'ah* was yes, you have to investigate the
entire נהרדעא *Nehardea*. Like, נהרדעא *Nehardea* is not just a city, right?
It's a whole region. Maybe it's a city, but anyway, it's a
little bit larger. Anyway, and you have to investigate the entire נהרדעא
*Nehardea* and to find out that there's nobody else that has exactly
those characteristics, you know, that has that name and whose wife has
that name. So you see we are concerned; we don't just assume
it's the person we think it's talking about. ורבא אמר
*ve-Rava amar*, רבא Rava, *Rava* says, אי איתא *ei ita*, יבדוק כולי
עלמא מיבעי ליה *yidbok kulei alma mibei leh*. No, that can't be.
If we really could not make, draw logical conclusions, then you would
have to check the entire world. Why would you have to check
the entire world? It says from נהרדעא *Nehardea*. Because he says נהרדעא
*Nehardea*, maybe נהרדעא *Nehardea* just means that that's where he was when
he was writing the גט *get*. אלא
*ela*,
I think רש"י *Rashi* says that. Yes, שמא אנדרולינאי אחר היה בנהרדעא
והלך לו *shema Androlinai acher haya bi-Nehardea ve-halakh lo*, right, maybe he's
not even, or maybe there was a guy living here, and he
no longer lives here. Maybe he was living here when the גט
*get* was written. So you know, when would there ever be an
end to that if you had to be concerned with those things?
אלא *ela*, says רבא Rava *Rava*, rather, משום כבודו דאבוה דשמואל הוא
דשלח הכי *mishum kevodo de-avuh de-Shmuel hu de-shalach hakhi*. The reason he
said, "Yes, you should check it out," it was to, you know,
in because to show respect to the father of שמואל *Shmuel*. The
father of שמואל *Shmuel* raised this question, and rather than saying it's
a stupid question, "Of course it's the guy you know," he said,
"You know what, you'd better check it out." It gave אבוה דשמואל
*avuh de-Shmuel* a lot of work to do, but he said that
rather than just saying, "You know, you don't have to worry about
it," which is pretty funny since when do we sort of do
that and let's say they, let's say, you know, it takes a
long time and the wife isn't able to remarry during that time.
So it seems to go be going a pretty far way to
say to give an answer that is not really necessary just not
to... But anyway, that's what רבא Rava says. So רבא says once
it seems that the guy, once you have somebody that fits those
specifics, you don't have to be concerned that there was somebody else
who also fits the exact same specifics.
Okay. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא, מנא אמינא לה, where do
I know this point that you don't have to be concerned there's
somebody else that fits those specifics? דהנו תרי
שטרי דנפיק במחוזא, D'hano trei shtarei d'nafik bimchoza, there are two documents
that came out
of מחוזא, Mechoza, וכתבו בהו v'chasvu behu בר ניגאי ונינאי בר חבי
Bar Nigai uNinai bar Chavi and it was written in them that
there were two that there were
two people's names were written on them, one guy's name was בר
ניגאי Bar Nigai and the other was נינאי בר חבי, Ninai bar
Chavi, so apparently חבי בר ניגאי Chavi bar Nigai and the other
was ניגאי בר חבי, Nigai bar Chavi, almost have like a mirror
image names. Okay, and these were like IOUs, these were written from
a creditor to a debtor or from a debtor to a creditor.
Okay. ואגבי בהו רבא בר אבוה זוזי, V'agbi behu Rava bar Avuha
zuzei, and רבא
בר אבוה Rava bar Avuha found that they were allowed somebody to
collect with them even though maybe somebody else had a
similar name. והא חבי בר ניגאי ונינאי בר חבי במחוזא שכיחי טובא,
Veha Chavi bar Nigai veNinai
bar Chavi beMechoza shchichi tuva, and he says these are very common
names, right? So it was like Shimon ben Reuven and Yaakov ben
Levi, right? And these were the names. I mean, you could tell
that they were common names because both the creditor and the debtor
had similar names, and nevertheless, he basically said that the guy holding
the document can assume to be the creditor and it's not exactly
clear how you know which guy was the debtor if there were
other people that had similar names. But somehow based on the context
of who was in the same city or whatever type of thing,
you can assume that they're the people we assume them to be
and you don't have to be concerned that there might be somebody
else even when it's reasonable there are other names. We do not
have to be concerned about that, we can use the context to
make us assume who it is referring to. So that's his proof.
So ואביי v'Abaye and ואביי v'Abaye would say back, למאי ניחוש לה?
lemaei neichosh lah? No, what do we have to be concerned about?
אי
לנפילה,
ei l'nefilla,
אי לנפילה, ei l'nefilla, if you're concerned that maybe he dropped it,
creditors don't drop their IOUs. So we're not concerned that another guy
the creditor dropped it and another guy with the same name found
it. מיזהר בה. mizahar beh.
אי לפיקדון, ei l'pikadon, if maybe we're afraid that he gave it
to somebody else for safekeeping who had the same name and the
creditor gave it to somebody else and this guy is misusing it
to collect for himself? כיון דשמיה כשמיה לא מפקד גביה, keivan d'shmei
k'shmei lo mafkad gabei, nobody is stupid enough, creditor to give
this IOU to another person who has exactly his same name and
then he can go ahead and use it to collect. So he
wouldn't have given it, so he wouldn't have dropped it, he wouldn't
have intentionally given it to some person for safekeeping. So who else
would it be that's holding onto it except the guy whose name
it's written in? מאי אמרת? mai amart? דילמא מסר ליה? dilma masar
leh? Maybe he gave it to somebody, you
know, he transferred the IOU to somebody else and he transferred it
but he did not
ultimately finish the acquisition so this other guy is holding onto it
but he does
not actually he hasn't actually acquired the debt. So no, אותיות נקנות
במסירה, osiyos niknos b'mesira, the very act of handing it over would
have transferred the debt. So basically we're not afraid that somebody else
other than the creditor is holding onto it. The creditor would not
have dropped it accidentally, he wouldn't have intentionally given it to some
person for safekeeping, and if he intended to sell it to this
person and we don't have to be concerned that the sale wasn't
finalized because the very act of giving is the finalization of the
sale. Of course the funny thing is that it might very well
be that this person is the one
that is the right creditor, but how do we know the debtor
is the right debtor also? The question to be asked is what
are they saying? I mean, obviously the creditor is saying it's him,
but what's the debtor saying? I mean, if the debtor isn't challenging
that this guy's the creditor and the debtor isn't challenging that he's
the debtor, what else would we be concerned about? And if the
debtor, so was it the case if the debtor was challenging that
this was the guy? I mean, if the debtor was denying that
he was the debtor, right, what allows us to assume that this
is the debtor? There's no good, it doesn't seem that that's clear.
So you have to sort of try to speculate what exactly the
case here was. The case that would make the most sense is
that the debtor was admitting that he was the debtor but challenging
that this guy was the creditor. And that's why אביי is able
to say, no, then the circumstances are good enough evidence of what's
what. But anyway we have from one extreme
of
questioning even with a lot of identifying marks, יצחק ריש גלותא the
son of the sister, etc., etc. that maybe we have to question
whether it's the person that fits. those criteria,
and then we have a middle case of again somebody who has
pretty good identifying marks, his name, his wife's name, his town's name,
not as much as the ריש גלותא case. And now we have
a case where things seem to be actually lacking in a good
degree of identification and it seems that אביי and רבא disagree on
the whole range of cases. The last case we must admit, if
it's a little questionable about who the debtor is, it is very
hard to understand רבא's position. What is the evidence that you're dealing
with the right debtor? But anyway, it is interesting. There seems to
be a wide range of cases whether we can make assumptions. Now,
this is, before we end we should point out that this is
relevant two ways. Number one it's relevant just because we want to
know about remarrying, allowing a woman to remarry. So when there are
reports and about coming from a distance and they're giving people's names,
can we assume that those names are the persons we're referring to?
But it is also worth pointing out the parallel of this to
the idea of אמר בי דידי הוה Amar Bi-Didei Havai and drawing
and connecting the dots based on context. Because if we're concerned that
there was a house that was filled with smoke and there were
arrows being shot and maybe she thought the guy was dead and
he wasn't really dead and the whole concern is drawing conclusions, well
we've already dealt with a few cases of drawing conclusions. We drew,
maybe drawing conclusions with a charred body, maybe drawing conclusions with
the bodies that were lifted up but okay that was maybe a
little bit more reasonable, drawing conclusions about what's in the barrel types
of cases. But more significantly here is drawing conclusions based on whose
name it is. We get a report of a certain name and
we're going to connect some dots and make some assumptions. So there
very often are cases where we connect the dots and make assumptions
based on context about what exactly happened or who's exactly being referred
to. And that really remains the point. It's one thing to say
the woman was incorrectly drawing those conclusions, but very often those are,
we're not going to have all the facts and we're going to
have to sort of connect some of the dots ourselves and one
way the issue of connecting the dots is not, is this the
same body that we lifted up out of the ocean or did
the person really die or is this the same body that got
charred and burnt, but when we have a report about a specific
name do we know who this name is referring to? Okay so
we will continue with this discussion when we resume tomorrow hopefully in
person.